All right, so, hey, guys.
Thanks for coming
to our second class.
Today we have the pleasure
of welcoming Fei Xia.
He's a senior research scientist
at Google DeepMind, where
he works on the robotics team.
He received his
PhD here, actually,
working with Silvio
Saverese and Stanford Vision
and Learning Lab, as
well as [INAUDIBLE]..
And his mission is to build
intelligent, embodied agents
that can interact with complex
and unstructured real world
environments with applications
like home robotics.
And recently, he
has been exploring
the use of foundation models for
robot decision making and action
generation.
So now I'll hand it off to Fei.
Hi, everyone.
I'm super happy to be
here and happy to be back.
I graduated from
here two years ago.
And now I'm a research
scientist at Google DeepMind.
I work on the robotics team.
And today I will be talking
about "Low-level Embodied
Intelligence with
Foundation Models."
So it's definitely
an interesting topic.
And I will introduce what
is embodied intelligence
and what is low-level
embodied intelligence,
and how we can accelerate
the building of them
with foundation models.
All right, so why are we working
on embodied intelligence?
So embodied intelligence
is an integral part
of artificial intelligence.
And it's an important
milestone to artificial general
intelligence.
And it has a lot of use cases.
Like, for example, we all hope
we have a home robot that can be
in our home 24/7 and
clean the home for us,
or clean up our messy
room, or cook for us,
or take care of our
aging family members.
So we are not quite there yet.
In fact, we are
quite far from it.
That is because our
intelligence is currently mostly
in the virtual world.
So we have AI agents that can
help us draft emails, or write
eloquent essays,
but they are not
super good at interacting
with the messy, real world,
unstructured,
complex environment
that a human resides in.
So just to give you guys
a couple of examples
of how messy the
real world can be
and how hostile it
could be to robotics,
I want to show you a curious
mistake or curious error
from one of our robots.
So the task is to put
the Coke can in the sink.
And watch what the robot does.
The robot grabs the Coke
can and opens the tap.
So this is kind of dangerous,
but it's kind of interesting,
because we never expect it
would do something like that.
It's just from random noise.
It starts to open the tap, and
the water starts coming out.
So for an agent to have this
type of physical intelligence,
it needs to understand
the effect of its actions
and what is so-called
a world model.
So people have been complaining
that language models so far
don't have a world model.
So it doesn't
understand geometry.
It doesn't understand the
spatial relationship of objects
or the effect of
actions, basically how
an object will move
according to physical laws.
So we are not quite there yet.
In another case--
so this is our robot
that is ready to deliver a can,
or actually throw away a can.
But as you can see, we have
this pre-programmed behavior
of tucking the arm behind.
And in doing that, the
can is upside down.
So if there is any
liquid in the can,
it will spill and
damage the robot.
So it's another example of
real world is really complex,
and there are a lot
of things to model.
And in order for
our robots to have
this sort of ambient
intelligence,
it really needs to understand
a lot of very nuanced details
of the environment
and understanding
the physics, physical laws,
and understanding effect
of its actions.
How do we do that?
There are many ways to
achieve embodied intelligence.
Actually, throughout
my PhD study,
I've been fascinated by
this idea of creating
interactive environments.
Basically, let an
agent explore in
these interactive environments.
Basically, create environments
that are complex enough
so that if the agent needs to
survive in such environment,
it must develop intelligence.
So it's an ecological view
of perception and agency,
and it's popularized by American
psychologist James J. Gibson.
So he has a famous quote, "Ask
not what is inside your head,
but what your head
is inside of."
So humans learn this type
of embodied intelligence.
A human is able to manipulate
objects effortlessly,
one, because of
evolution, second,
because the
childhood experience.
We have been playing
with this toy.
We have been interacting
with this toy
and watched the physical
effect so that we learn.
And similarly, we can
give robots a safe playpen
so they can explore
in those environment,
and interact with
the environment,
and play, and watch
the effect of actions,
and effectively understand how
to manipulate those objects.
So I have been developing
this simulation environment,
one of which is called a
Gibson environment, which
is published as CVPR.
It's mainly aiming at simulating
the visual world faithfully
and also simulate the
physical world to some extent.
So we built this environment,
which is a scanned environment,
from a lot of houses,
and then an agent,
we can spawn an agent in that,
in this case, a humanoid agent,
and the agent can learn to walk,
or to run in this environment,
and simulate all this
perception information.
So we can create a perception
action loop for this agent.
And similarly, we can
put other types of agent
in this environment.
In this case, a little cart.
And we can also put a
quadruped, or this ant
into this environment.
So essentially, we
create an environment
where we can simulate
perception for the agent,
and then we can create
a neural network
to map the perception to action.
And this way, we achieve some
sort of physical intelligence.
It's mostly for
navigation and locomotion.
This is not enough.
So in this case, the environment
is one monolithic piece of mesh.
As you can see, the
agent ran into the wall,
and it bounced back.
So there's no articulation
in this environment.
So it's not simulating the full
complexity of the environment.
So the things that we
can do with our agent
is rather limited.
So that's why we create other
simulation environments,
one of which is iGibson
environment, which
is called Interactive Gibson.
So what we do is we create--
we, again, scan a lot
of real world houses,
and then we convert
them to CAD assets,
basically, mesh assets
that are interactable.
In this case, we have
a simulated agent
that goes into the environment,
and then closes all the drawers.
So we are able to do that
because we model the complexity
of the world a little bit more.
We go beyond just
modeling the visual world.
We start to model physics
a little bit more.
Basically, modeling the degree
of freedom in the environment,
and our agent can do more
than just navigating around.
So we can go even further.
So we can even model
more degrees of freedom.
And our agent can develop
more complicated behavior,
such as unloading a
dishwasher and finding a bowl,
or take out a bowl, and
put it on the table.
So as we scale up the
complexity of the environment,
we are able to learn much
more complicated skills
in the simulation.
And that's one way to achieve
embodied intelligence, which
is to build a complex enough
simulation environment.
Not just in my research, but the
entire field of computer vision
is undergoing a paradigm shift.
So previously, we are
focusing on internet AI.
We curate a lot of
internet data sets
to study problems, like
classification, segmentation,
and detection.
Basically, all these
computer vision problems.
Now, we focus a lot
more on embodied AI,
which is adding the action
dimension to the problem.
We are studying problems like
visual navigation, manipulation,
rearrangement, embodied
question answering, instruction
following.
And the simulators replace--
in some sense replace the
original role of data sets.
One thing that doesn't
change, which is the data
is still super important.
We are still relying
on large amount of data
to learn this
intelligent behavior,
no matter it's from a static
data set or from a simulator.
So learning a simulation can
take a lot of interactions.
So just to give you an
example, we create this iGibson
environment, and we want to
learn a behavior called "Go
into a room through
a closed door."
So this is a rather
simple behavior,
which I can show on the
top right of the screen.
So the agent needs to
stop in front of the door.
It needs to stop at
the right distance.
If it stops too close to the
door, it cannot extend its arm.
If it's too far, it
cannot open the door.
And then it basically
opens the door.
Let me play this again.
It opens the door.
When there is enough clearance,
it will go into the door.
However, it takes about 50,000
episodes or 1.25 million
environment interactions to
learn this type of behavior.
This is because we are using
model-free reinforcement
learning.
The agent is exploring
this environment.
It could really push any point.
It could rather
stop at any point.
So we give it a reward
function to go into the room.
But it's very rare that it will
stumble upon this behavior.
I would like to argue
with foundation models,
we can do a lot more different.
So what do you do?
Nowadays, you just ask ChatGPT.
How do you go into a room
through a closed door?
And it will say, open the door.
Walk through the door.
So this is a gross
simplification of the problem.
Of course, the problem
is not that simple.
But what I'm just
saying is that we
can leverage a lot of semantic
prior from the foundation
models.
So if we really lack data, if
we really need a lot of data,
the foundation model
is a compressed version
of the entire data, and
it's a knowledge base
that you can query to accelerate
the development of robotics.
Of course, simulation
and real world data
is still super, super important.
But maybe we can get
the best of both worlds.
We can use foundation
models, plus a limited
amount of simulation
or real world data.
So that's what I'm going
to talk about today.
So where are we in terms of
foundation models plus robotics?
So our team at
Google DeepMind has
been piloting in foundation
model plus robotics.
So we developed advanced
planning, high-level planning
algorithms.
One of the first is
called PaLM-SayCan.
It is an algorithm that
can parse a user command.
So here is a demo.
Here is a scenario.
Here is a user command.
I spilled my Coke on the table.
How would you throw
it away and bring me
something to help clean?
And it's querying
a large language
model, which is given a
score, highlighted in blue.
And there's also an
affordance score.
The affordance will tell you
whether an action at a given
state is possible.
It's augmenting
the language model
to give you only
possible things.
So essentially, it is
doing the planning,
doing the semantic planning
with the language model,
but it's also taking into
consideration what it can do.
So it's not just outputting--
the language model
tends to hallucination.
It doesn't hallucinate.
It only gives you what is
possible for the robot to do
and what is actionable
for the robot.
And the robot is doing the
thing that is advancing
the long horizon task progress.
And also, each task is
executed by a low-level policy.
Here, it doesn't
quite clean the table
because we haven't added
this to the low-level skill.
But imagine, there
is a low-level skill
to clean the table.
It will finish the entire thing.
What is the local
policy used to hear?
The local policy used to hear
is Robotic Transformer 1.
It's our team's home
grown transformer.
Essentially, we collect
a large data set
of human demonstrations.
We put the transformer, and
we train it on this large data
set of expert trajectories.
It is able to do about 700
tasks with 97% success rate.
And it has interesting
generalization behavior.
It can operate in a new kitchen
it has never seen before,
which is showing there is a
successful recipe to apply
foundation models in robotics.
So that's roughly where are we
in terms of foundation model
plus robotics.
And I will talk about a few
new works that is bringing this
to the next level.
So actually, my teammate Ted
gave a talk of foundation models
plus robotics at the
beginning of this year.
It's also this class CS25.
I highly recommend it.
It's available on YouTube.
I actually watched it
last night so that I don't
repeat some of the contents.
But what he basically
mentioned is that we--
he revealed our team's
progress in terms of building
this robotic foundation models.
And we have had a lot
of somewhat detour,
and now we started to
figure out a recipe.
So in 2021 to 2022 is how
we scale to many tasks
with demonstrations.
How do we collect a
large amount of data?
In fact, about 100,000
demonstrations.
And we tried different
ways to do it.
We tried the behavior cloning.
We tried imitation learning
plus reinforcement learning,
and some other ways,
or combining them
with language models,
such as SayCan.
In 2022 to 2023, it's about
how we can leverage foundation
models to accelerate robotics.
We really see a proliferation
of using foundation models
to accelerate robotics, both
on the high-level planning
and low-level control,
probably leaning more
towards the high-level planning.
So if the recipe works--
so the recipe is essentially
combine a large scale,
diverse offline data
set with a high capacity
architecture, such
as a transformer,
and using language
as a universal glue.
So this would be the recipe
to build foundation models
for robotics.
So if this recipe
works, what do we do?
What do we do next?
Essentially, we
just-- let's just
scale everything to
two orders of magnitude
and be done with it,
and solve robotics.
And guess what.
That's what we did.
So that's the end
of the lecture.
Maybe we can cut this
a little bit short.
And that's a joke.
That's not happening.
So we are still on
our way on our quest
to solve low-level
embodied intelligence.
When I talk to people that
you can use foundation models
to do robotics, their
reaction would be it's mostly
doing high-level reasoning.
It doesn't do the low-level
manipulation really well.
And that's for a reason.
One of the reasons is
there's Moravec's paradox.
Moravec's paradox
is the observation
that in artificial
intelligence and robotics,
contrary to traditional
assumptions or our intuitions,
reasoning requires very
little computation.
But sensorimotor control
and perception skills
require enormous
compute resources.
That is because as
biological creatures,
we acquire the sensorimotor
skills through evolution.
This is very different.
So we might not be
able to reason or do
large amount of large
scale computation,
but this sensorimotor control
is integral to our survival.
So it's essentially
already learned in our DNA.
But in robotics, it's
a little bit different.
So the chips are very good at
doing reasoning and computation,
but they are not
super good-- they
haven't experienced the world.
They haven't acquired
the sensorimotor skills
that are necessary for them
to do tasks in the real world.
Here is an example.
When the computer beat Kasparov,
basically, the human champion
in chess, there is not a robot
arm moving the chess piece.
It can beat the human
champion in chess,
but there's still someone that
needs to move the chess piece.
Similarly, in the
AlphaGo moment,
when Lee Sedol was
beaten by AlphaGo.
There's still someone who is
moving the chess piece for them.
It's not a robot doing that.
So this is showing
the reasoning is--
the hard things are easy,
and the easy things are hard.
There's another thing
that prevents us
from using foundation
models more prevalently,
more in larger scale
in robotics, which
is the training data bias.
The training data of foundation
models or large language models
are mostly language tasks.
So it's perhaps not
that surprising it
knows how to clean up a
kitchen, because maybe there
are wikiHow articles teaching
you how to clean up a kitchen,
or to do something
in a procedural way.
But there is no wikiHow
articles teaching you
how to move your finger 5
centimeters to the left,
because people just
don't say that.
People don't write that down.
So there is a very
limited amount
of this low-level control data
in large language model training
corpora.
So we do have a
lot of challenges
in bringing the foundation
models to a lower level.
So that's what I mean by
low-level embodied intelligence.
So any questions so far?
I also want to make
this quite interactive.
So if there is any
questions, feel
free to interrupt me any time.
All right, if not,
we can continue.
So there are a
couple of challenges
of using large language
models for low-level control.
As I just mentioned, the
first thing is lack of data.
So we only have perhaps 100,000
episodes of human demonstration
data.
And it takes about 13
robots 17 months to collect.
So it's a huge amount of effort.
On the contrary, large language
models are trained on the order
of 1,000 billion tokens.
PaLM, smaller PaLM, was trained
on 780 billion parameters--
780 billion tokens.
And the larger one is trained--
following the
Chinchilla rule, you
would need to train it
on 1.35 trillion tokens.
So it's a huge
amount of discrepancy
between how much data we
can achieve in robotics
and how much we can get
in large language models.
So we will always be
bounded by robotic data.
So maybe we can scale
on other fronts.
Maybe we can keep the
robotics data the same,
and then we can scale
on other fronts.
Like maybe we can scale
the pre-training mix
of text and image, or
maybe image and text pairs.
Maybe we can build this
cake, and the robotics data
is just a cherry on top of it.
And we can scale the
foundation really, really well.
Some of my work that I'm
going to talk about today
actually reused the RT-1 data.
We don't collect
new data for RT-2.
But we want to do more things
with the same amount of data.
The second challenge is kind of
related to the first challenge.
Language models lack an
interface for low-level control.
If you ask a language model,
"How do you make a robot dog
stand up on two feet?", it will
tell you a lot of things that
sound reasonable,
sound plausible.
It will tell you the robot
dog's torso is upright,
balanced over two hind feet, and
standing shoulder width apart.
This is great.
This is all great, but we
cannot put it on the robot.
On the other hand, maybe
we can ask a language model
to write control code to
directly control the robot.
But usually, that
requires you to curate
an API that is friendly
to the language model.
If you directly ask it to
give you my joint angles
to make the robot
stand upright, it
will not give you
the right thing
because it doesn't
have enough context.
So essentially,
large language models
don't speak robot language.
Can we actually find the
right robot language?
Can we find the interface
between large language models
and robot control?
Or can we just treat robot
action as another language?
So that's what we
want to find out.
So in today's agenda,
I will be talking
about low-level embodied
intelligence with foundation
models.
It's separated into
two parts, and it's
addressing the two challenges
that I've just mentioned.
Part one is about model
consolidation, joint scaling,
and positive transfer.
So I have to put
them in one part
because they are
somewhat related.
And part two is developing a
new interface of large language
models.
So what do I mean by
model consolidation?
Model consolidation--
yes, question--
Yeah, I'm just going to ask
why couldn't you just fine tune
an LLM for generating specific
low-level code, either some text
description [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
That's a good question.
So the question is, why cannot
we fine tune a language model
to directly output low-level
code or like robot actions?
So I would be talking
about RT-2, which
does somewhat similar to that.
It fine tunes a language
model to output action
as a language to output
our action representation.
There are certain downsides to
that, like, for example, you
would need to collect additional
data to fine tune a language
model.
So either we can fine tune that,
or we can use a language model
zero shot if you find the
right interface, which
I will talk about a little
bit in the part two.
[INAUDIBLE] without fine tuning?
Without fine tuning, yeah.
So the model consolidation
is-- essentially,
we can do the high-level
reasoning and low-level control
in one model.
And joint scaling is not only
we scale the robot data, which
is expensive, we also scale
the pre-training data,
or we already start from a
pre-trained vision language
model, and the positive
transfer is the model benefiting
from diverse joint training
across internet scale, language,
vision, and vision language
domains combined with robotics.
So this is a
continuation of the axes
that Ted drew in
his previous talk.
So we can see there is a trend.
So this visualization
basically highlights
some of the work of our team.
And each work, each
column is basically
a robotic system that is able
to do both high-level reasoning
and low-level control.
So previously, we needed to have
separate models for each thing.
Previously, in the
initial release of SayCan,
the planning is done by
a large language model,
and the affordance is done
by TQ-Opt, like policy
trained with sim2real.
And the low-level policy
is robotic transformer one.
So it's each model doing
its dedicated thing.
And we need to train each
model differently and perhaps
with different types of data.
And later, we have
Q-transformer, which unifies,
which is a kind of an offline
RL method that is leveraging
transformer architecture.
So it's a high
capacity architecture.
It can train on both positive
data and negative data.
And with that, we are able to
gather a policy that is also
understanding affordances.
So we can unify the low-level
policy and affordances.
But the planning is still
a large language model.
And then we have PaLM-E,
which is a vision language
model, which is a
large language model,
also trained on vision
language domain.
So the PaLM-E can do
planning and affordance
in just one model, but the
low level is still using RT-1.
And finally, we unify
everything together,
like there is RT-2,
which I'm going
to talk about today, that can
do both high-level planning
to some extent,
generating affordance,
and do low-level policies.
So behind the
model consolidation
is the consolidation of tasks.
We can represent every task as
a vision plus text to text task.
So it's a really universal
representation of the task.
And then with
that, you can train
it really using a lot of data.
And you can see
positive transfer.
Basically learning
affordance can also
tell you how to achieve a task.
There are a transfer
between tasks when you
pull all the tasks together.
So to understand
this joint scaling
and to understand the
model consolidation,
we need to understand
PaLM-E a little bit.
So PaLM-E is an embodied
multi-modal language model.
It's based on the
PaLM architecture.
So PaLM is a large
language model.
We made some adaptation
on the architecture
so it can understand
multimodal input.
So it is basically
one model that
is able to take in
multimodal input.
So in large language
models, each word
is tokenized, and
tokenized, and getting
this embedding of these words.
And then that is fed into
a large language model.
So in PaLM-E, what we do
is instead of using words,
we can use multimodal tokens.
So the multimodal
tokens can come
from a vision
language-- can come
transformer, a ViT,
or it can come from
robot sensory data.
So every multimodal
token, then we
map it to the text
embedding space.
We basically train
a linear affine
transform between the multimodal
token and the text embedding
space.
And then we can treat the
multimodal token as words
as well.
So essentially, we have a
language model as a solid base,
and then we start to adapt it
to understand multimodal tokens.
So this is quite interesting,
because we don't--
it doesn't require a ton
of adaptation or fine
tuning for it to understand
multimodal input.
It just aligns naturally
to the multimodal input,
such as images.
I will show a couple of
examples of what it can do.
And we can train the same way as
training large language models.
So essentially, we can reuse the
same infrastructure and training
algorithm and everything
to train this PaLM-E.
A couple other things
we find along the way
is positive transfer, which
I will share in a little bit.
So I guess here I
also want to mention
PaLM-E is one of the largest
models we have explored so far.
It has 562 billion
parameters, which
is by concatenating the PaLM 540
billion parameters and the 22
billion ViT.
And we find a lot of emergent
capabilities of these models.
That is we haven't expected
during training time,
but really, we can
prompt these models,
and ask it to do
interesting things.
We have also explored using
neural scene representation,
basically, an object-centric
representation fed into PaLM-E.
So object-centric
representation assigns one token
to each object.
And we find that
this representation
is super helpful
for robot planning
tasks, because traditional ViT
representation is based on grid,
and it doesn't have a full
understanding of layered objects
and their relationships.
We have done an extensive study
on the scaling performance
and the catastrophic
forgetting performance,
and all other interesting
experiments in the paper.
So please refer to
the paper for more.
So here I'm just showing some
interesting qualitative examples
of some emergent capability
of PaLM-E that we found out.
So first, we found this model
has some reasoning capability.
You can give it an image and
ask it questions that requires
a little bit of reasoning.
And you can prompt this
with, let's think step
by step, which is a technique
used to elicit reasoning
in large language models.
But here in multimodal language
models, you can do the same.
I guess people are
also experimenting it
these days with GPT-4V.
You can also prompt it to think
step by step or count, row
by row.
But here this is before GPT-4V.
And we were able
to elicit reasoning
using some of the
interesting prompts, such
as we can ask it, in
this photo, are there
more cats or more dogs?
Let's think step by step.
And they found--
the PaLM-E found out
there are an equal
amount of dogs and cats.
And on the right,
given an image,
can I go down this street
on a bicycle, yes or no?
Let's think step by step.
And the reply is, do not enter.
Second, except the bicycles.
Do not entry except bicycles.
Yes.
So it's doing this
modus of reasoning.
And it's mixing this
understanding of symbols,
and also mixing the
understanding of text.
So this is quite amazing to me.
To be honest, when
I first saw this,
I didn't expect a
multimodal language
model would be able to do that.
And we also tried one thing,
which is traditionally
very difficult to language
models, which is to tell a joke.
Language models can
understand joke,
but sometimes it just doesn't--
it's not able to
tell you a joke, when
it comes to the punchline,
because it's just
trying to make something
that is plausible
and sounds like a joke.
And when it comes
to a punchline,
it doesn't really
know what to say.
So here I give it an
image, and I asked it
to come up with a description.
And then it comes
up with a joke.
So this guides the language
model to think step by step.
And the description is a
donkey is carrying a dog, cat,
and rooster.
And the joke is, what
do you call a donkey
with a rooster on his back?
A rooster booster.
It's so creative.
Like, when I saw this,
I'm pleasantly surprised.
And I searched online.
I couldn't find
another joke like that.
So it's actually an
original joke by PaLM-E.
And finally, we see some maths
reasoning with this model.
Basically, I give it a messy
menu from a pizza store.
And I ask it, how much is--
I'm just buying a pizza
for me and my friend.
How much should I pay?
Let's think step by step.
And it's figuring out there is
a pizza, and there's a $9.99.
And it tells you the price.
In some of the answers,
it even calculates text.
But the text is hallucinated,
so that doesn't work.
All right, let's talk
about positive transfer.
So apart from the amazing
capabilities-- amazing things
that PaLM-E can do, it also has
interesting positive transfer
behavior.
So when we train PaLM-E on a
single domain, when we train it
on just a single robotics
task, the performance
is not super great.
But when we pull all
the data together
and we also include internet
scale visual language tasks,
such as captioning,
visual question answering,
it is able to do much better.
So this shows that it's
important to mix all the data
together and train it jointly.
The internet scale data can
act as a regularizer for you
to not forget the
representations.
And those representations
are, in turn, very useful
for robotics.
So that's the positive
transfer results.
And we start to see
more and more positive
transfer in other
of our studies.
Yes.
So how much did that do to do
proactive, like in simulation
or in real world?
I think the playing with
sorting stuff in [? policy, ?]
is very impressive.
Right.
That's a very good point.
So for the-- so these
are all planning
data, high-level planning.
Maybe let's just talk
about two things.
So first of all, the sorting
results, the low-level policy
is still using a
traditional controller.
So it's using a
policy called LAVA.
And that policy is trained
on 68,000 episodes.
The high-level planning is
probably easier than you think,
because it only needs to tell--
put the-- it's giving commands
to the low-level policy.
So it basically
only needs to say,
put the red block
into top left corner.
Put another red block
into the top left corner.
So it's rather a quite standard
autoregressive language modeling
task.
The only thing you need
to do is to determine
what task is not finished yet.
So, for example, if the block
is already in the corner,
it shouldn't call another policy
to move it to the corner again.
So it's rather like
understanding--
parsing the states and
understanding the states.
So this high-level policy
only requires about 50 to 100
demonstrations to learn.
So it's quite
parameter efficient.
And in the future--
that's a very good question,
actually-- in the future,
a lot of these tasks can
be taught in context.
So maybe you just demonstrate
it once to the large language
model, then it knows
how to do that.
How can a large language model
know which low-level policy
it needs?
Yeah, this is through human
demonstration as well.
So a human on a low level can
demonstrate a low-level policy
by teleoperating a robot
to do a certain task.
But on a high
level, it could also
just give the low-level policy.
Imagine your control
interface is through text.
And then you can--
as a human, you can also
guide a low-level policy
to accomplish a task.
And then that thing can then be
used to train a large language
model.
So that's for the sorting block.
The second is a little
bit more interesting
because the planning steps are
actually generated by PaLM.
So we essentially distilled
PaLM plus this affordance model
into PaLM-E. So that's a
little bit more interesting.
That's like using the AI
data to bootstrap itself.
That one has about
3,000 episodes.
Also, not quite a lot, but it's
able to learn complex planning
behavior, replanning
behavior, error recovery,
which I will show in this slide.
So with the PaLM-E as
a high-level planner,
we are able to take the rice
chips out of the drawer.
And there is a twist, which is I
will be messing with the robot.
And so as it put it
onto the counter,
I put it back to the drawer.
And as it picked it up again,
and then I put it back again.
So it's able to
understand the state.
It's able to understand
my task is not finished.
I cannot proceed
with the next task.
Now, after I don't
mess with it anymore,
it's able to close the drawer
and pick up the bag of chips.
So PaLM-E is able to combine
affordance and planning in one
model and do complex
reasoning of the scene
and the environment.
And interestingly, we can use
the exact same model checkpoint
to do block sorting as well.
So this is the same
model checkpoint.
It can not only reason about
how to bring a bag of chips
to a user.
It can also sort blocks.
And it's also responding to
adversarial perturbation,
like if the user is putting
the block in the middle again,
it's able to recover from that.
So these are all coming
from the same model.
And it can also tell jokes.
So yeah, that's just the power
of vision language models.
Now, we want to
go a level deeper.
These are all visual
language models
that are used for planning
or high-level reasoning.
Can we use them for
low-level control?
It turns out we can.
And that's the RT-2 work, which
is the vision language action
model that transfers web
knowledge to robotic control.
What can it do?
When asked, pick up
the extinct animal
and it has a whole range
of objects on the table,
it will pick up the dinosaur.
So it can link
the extinct animal
to dinosaur and to the action
to pick the dinosaur up.
So it's really doing like this
emergent reasoning, and also
the manipulation in
just the one model.
And by the way,
this robot hasn't
seen any of these before,
at least in the robot
training data.
It might have seen this
in the internet catalog.
But it has never seen it in
the robotics training data.
So it's quite interesting
how we need to evaluate
these robots nowadays.
So when we evaluate
language models,
to prevent data
contamination, every time
you need to give it new
questions, because, otherwise,
it might have already
memorized it in its training.
When we evaluate these robots,
we actually go to a dollar store
to buy all these toys to make
sure it hasn't seen that before.
And as we run more
evaluations, maybe there
will be some
replication as well.
But as you can see, it
is able to understand
to pick up this dinosaur toy.
How did we do that?
So we start from
a vision language
model that is trained
on internet scale data.
And then we also combine it with
robotics action data, which is
the RT-1 data, and we get RT-2.
And we can dive deeper, a
little bit deeper into RT-2.
So first of all, what is
a vision language model?
A vision language
model is a transformer
that takes in image and
text, and then outputs text.
So within Google, there's
a vision language model
called PaLI, which is
an encoder-decoder type
of architecture.
It's basically having a ViT
to understand images, and then
a transformer encoder and
the transformer decoder.
They encompass both the
visual and semantics
to understand the world.
In the robotics, we have to deal
with a lot of both of these.
And the question
is, can we leverage
the knowledge in the
visual language models
and apply them to robotics?
On the other hand,
we have the RT-1.
If you want to learn
more about RT-1,
you can listen to the previous
episode of this CS25 by Ted.
So he gave a detailed
introduction on the RT-1.
But the RT-1, if you
stand far enough,
it is also a vision language
to action or something model.
It takes in human instruction.
It takes in the
current camera image.
The camera image passes through
a film efficient net, which
is tokenized into
81 tokens, and then
going to a token learner,
which compresses everything
into eight tokens.
And then there is
a transformer block
leveraging a lot of
self-attention layer,
and then generates actions.
The action is also tokenized.
The robot has seven
degrees of freedom.
Basically, the end
effector has six degrees
of freedom, its
position and rotation,
and the gripper
can open and close.
And there is another
dimension representing
terminate the episode or not.
Terminating means my
task is already done.
And we discretize every
dimension into 256 bins.
And then we do cross
entropy loss on those bins.
So that's RT-1
architecture in a nutshell.
It's quite similar to
a vision language model
with different output tokens.
So it's rather
natural that we just
use a large pre-trained
vision language model directly
as policy.
We can use the PaLI
or PaLM-E as a policy.
And one question is, how
do we deal with actions
when using pretrained
visual language models?
And here is the actual
representation that we use.
The robot actions here
are the eight dimensions.
And as I mentioned, there's
termination, position change,
and rotation change.
And we discretize
everything into 256 bins.
We also have tried other
alternative representations,
but they are not as good as
just this naive representation.
Yes.
Can you go back to
the previous slide?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE],, what is
FILM EfficientNet?
The FILM EfficientNet is a
pretrained convolutional neural
network.
It's used to
tokenize the images.
So the reason that we do this
is through some ablation study,
we can tokenize the
image in different ways.
We can tokenize in ResNet.
We can tokenize
everything into ResNet.
And we can tokenize
using FILM EfficientNet.
FILM, what it means is it
also takes into the language
embedding and appends it
to the intermediate layers
of the ResNet.
So you basically have
some concatenation
of whatever sentence
you put in in images?
Yeah.
That goes through
this neural network,
this convolutional network?
That's right.
[INAUDIBLE] condition
[INAUDIBLE] transform it.
Self-attention output
goes to action training.
That's right.
It's action as in the code.
The action is not in code.
The action is in text.
It's basically
what is shown here.
This is the action.
It's eight numbers.
Each number ranges
from 0 to 255.
And maybe another note
on the FILM ResNet.
It's about how we
tokenize the images
and how we combine vision
information and language
information.
There are many ways to do that.
This is not the only way.
There is early fusion
and late fusion,
and there is also
cross-attention.
You can basically tokenize
your image just by itself.
And then you can have language
and use cross-attention
to combine the image
and text representation.
So here we are using this model.
This is RT-1 for robotics.
So we do have a lot of
considerations, such as latency.
That's why we use this FILM
ResNet, because it's super fast.
And it can output
a limited amount
of tokens, which we can further
compress with a token learner.
Yeah.
And is this autoregressive,
like every single image
it sees, it then [INAUDIBLE]?
Right.
So it is autoregressive, yeah.
And every time we use a
history of up to six steps,
so every time you see
this image right now,
and you see about 2 seconds
of history before it.
And this will be your input.
Again, if you have more
questions about RT-1,
I recommend watching
the previous episode.
And here is all about RT-2.
So we can convert the
string of numbers.
This will be our output
of our transformer, which
is a vision language model.
We tried other alternatives,
such as floating numbers.
Floating numbers is not super
friendly to language model
tokenizer because it has
these decimal points.
We also try the human language,
such as left or right.
It's more a semantic
representation,
but they cannot be directly
executed on a robot,
which is a limitation
of this method.
So if we commit to this action
representation, which is just
a string of numbers,
we essentially
get a vision language
action model.
We tried different
variants, including
PaLI-X. This is a Pathways
langauge image model.
It can-- there are a
5-billion parameter variant
and a 55-billion
parameter variant.
And we also tried PaLM-E,
which is 12 billion parameters.
The procedure that we
did to train this RT-2
is via fine tuning.
So fine tuning is to put
the internet scale data
and the robotic data together.
And then we fine tune it
on this mixture of data
so that it retains the
internet scale knowledge.
Maybe that's also an
artifact of our data
is too small and
not diverse enough.
So if you just fine
tune on robotics data,
it will quickly
overfit and forget
about all this
pretraining mixture.
Maybe it's a dynamic of scale.
So we'll see.
At inference time,
how do we do this?
We basically-- again, we
do this autoregressively.
We have an
instruction of a task.
And we format this as a
question and answering task.
What should the robot do
to achieve a certain task?
And the task is a string
that humans give the robot
for the robot to achieve.
And it also has the
current observation,
which is the robot observation,
the camera image, RGB image,
a pass through of
ViT, and then a pass
through of the large language
model, and then output
a list of tokens.
So we leverage constraint
decoding to make sure it always
has eight numbers,
because, otherwise,
we cannot detokenize it.
It's very easy for a language
model to just miss one number,
right?
So we do have some mechanism,
such as constraint decoding
and beam search to make
sure the format is correct.
After we get the string
of eight numbers,
we detokenize it to
a delta t and delta
r, which is the end
effector delta [INAUDIBLE]..
And the robot can just
directly run this on the robot.
After the run on the robot,
we repeat this process.
We get another new image,
run through this process,
and get the new action.
And we repeat this process
until a termination is decoded.
So some people
might be concerned
that this is rather slow.
It's, in fact, quite
slow, because it's
12 billion parameters
or 5 billion parameters.
We cannot run it on a robot.
So we run on a TPU
cluster, and the robot
is querying the TPU
cluster to get the numbers
and apply it on the robot.
So for the 12
billion parameters,
we can actually run at 10 hertz.
So it's quite fast.
For all of the model, we
can run at least 3 hertz.
So that is sufficient for
controlling our robot.
And we see a lot of emerging
skills that is not trained--
that is not on the training set.
Essentially, as
I just mentioned,
we are probing what
this RT-2 can do.
We actually don't know.
So we are trying to figure
out what the RT-2 can do.
So we test it with a lot
of new tasks, such as,
put a strawberry into
the correct bowl,
or move banana to
Germany, like just
to test its understanding
of symbols or flags.
Pick a land animal.
There's a horse.
There's an octopus.
But basically, test the
semantic reasoning, and also
low-level manipulation skills.
And we divide the tasks
into symbol understanding,
and reasoning, and human
recognition, and average.
We found with RT-1, which is not
trained on internet scale data.
We do quite poorly in these
emergent evaluation tasks.
And in the RT-2
variants, which is fine
tuned on the internet
data and on robotics data,
we do much better
in these tasks.
And there is also
an effect of scale.
So the RT-2 was a
55 billion PaLI.
It's performing better
than the 12 billion PaLM-E.
Although, they perform quite
similarly for in-domain tasks.
But the generalization
is kind of interesting.
It seems with larger scale,
you can generalize better.
And here are some videos of the
robot achieving these tasks,
like moving the
banana to a number.
Put the strawberry
into the correct bowl.
Move a Rubik's cube
to the water bottle.
But I'm speaking Chinese.
Moving the banana
to a German flag.
So it's able to do all of
these very interesting tasks.
In terms of the
quantitative evaluations,
we also found that
the attitude policy
is quite robust to unseen
objects, unseen backgrounds,
and unseen environments.
And here is another evidence
of positive transfer.
So co-fine-tuned with
VQA data outperforms
fine-tuning on robotics only.
And if you train on robot data
from scratch, it barely works.
It almost doesn't work because
it overfits to robot data,
and our robot data
is just too small.
So we do need to do
co-fine-tuning, or at least
the fine-tuning so it retains
its internet scale knowledge.
This is also a
recipe for how people
would develop a domain
specific vision language model.
So you start from a very
general vision language model,
and you fine tune
on your domain,
or you can co-fine-tune with
your specific domain data.
This is likely a problem
that each vertical
of artificial intelligence
would incur someday.
We can also test
on other platforms,
like this shows some
cross embodiment.
The RT-2 PaLI-3B outperforms
previous models in terms
of moving blocks around
a 2D environment.
So this is-- and in
large language models,
we have this chain of
thought reasoning, which
is a method to elicit reasoning
in large language models.
You can either do
zero [INAUDIBLE]
chain-of-thought
reasoning by saying,
let's think step by step.
I'll give it the
examples of reasoning.
It's basically
decoding more things,
and then come to the conclusion.
We can use a similar procedure
for the RT-2 as well.
So in the RT-2 PaLM-E,
instead of directly decoding
the actions, we can
actually decode a plan,
and then append it with actions.
So this gives the language
model an opportunity
to understand the question or
parse the question differently.
It also gives us the
opportunity to reason
about things a little bit.
For example, if you say, bring
me a drink, and it will, say,
pick up a 7up can because
there's a 7up can on the table.
So we synthesized a couple of
hundred such examples using
a large language model, just
by augmenting the instruction,
and then fine tune the RT-2 just
for a couple of hundred steps.
So it's between for fine
tuning and in-context learning.
And it's able to
do some reasoning.
And some of the
interesting reasoning tasks
include, I need
to hammer a nail.
Which object from the
scene might be useful?
And in the scene,
there is a headphone.
There is a rock.
And there is a sticky note.
And the robot will
say, rocks, and then
generate actions to
pick up the rock.
So it's interesting
that it's able to do
this self-reasoning with RT-2.
And here is a
demonstration of some
of the chain-of-thought
reasoning with RT-2 PaLM-E.
And the task is
pick up the thing
that is different from
all other objects.
And it picks up the chocolate
because this is a snack,
and the other things
are the drink.
And I can also speak
a different language.
And the plan would be to
translate it into a language
that it's familiar
with, which is English,
and then do the task.
There are also
potentially failure cases
of the chain-of-thought
reasoning.
So here, I say, move the
green objects together.
And as you can see,
the robot oscillates
between the two green
objects because there
are rather two plans.
It could move the can
to the bag of chips,
or it could move the
bag of chips to the can.
It oscillates between two
plans until one action,
bring it to an
object, and it will
commit to one of the
plans rather than another.
It's not always
guaranteed to work,
but it's quite interesting.
And it's also interesting
that, again, we
are testing the
manipulation policy,
like how we test intelligence
of humans, or animals, or kids,
because they're getting
more and more advanced.
As a summary, we have
the vision, language,
and action model that
is able to achieve--
improve the generalization.
It can do new tasks and
operate new objects.
It can also do
chain-of-thought reasoning.
And improving the
underlying model,
such as the vision language
model itself by scaling it up.
And trained with
internet scale data,
or trained with larger or higher
quality internet scale data,
we can achieve
better robot control,
which is quite amazing,
because robotics field has
been traditionally
developing quite slowly
and is bounded by
hardware, bounded
by a lot of different
things, bounded by operation.
But now it seems we can
piggyback on the development
of the foundation model field.
And whatever they do will
trickle down to our field
as well.
And the future will be to
increase the motion diversity
and extend on the
chain-of-thought reasoning
capability, and many more.
And so there is another example
of positive transfer, which
you might have seen recently.
So far I've been talking about
scaling differently, right?
I've been talking about
don't scale robotics data
and scale other data.
That's because robotics
data is so hard to collect.
And the purpose is not to
avoid collecting robotics data.
It's to develop a recipe
that you can do more
with limited robotics data.
However, there's also
an effort from our team
and the entire robotics
field to scale up
the robot data collection, which
is called the Open X Embodiment.
And the model train is called
RTX, Robotics Transformer
X. It's basically 22 type of
embodiments, and 572 skills,
and 60 data sets
pulled all together.
So this will be
the ultimate data
set we can use to study
positive transfer and to scale--
to study this joint scaling.
And there are already
evidences of positive transfer.
So we pulled all the data
together from all these labs
and find a common
action representation
that we can use to train
our robotic transformer.
And we have already found
this jointly trained model can
outperform a task-specific
model that is
developed in each of the labs.
So there is some benefits
in pulling all of the data
together.
So scaling robot data
is also quite important.
So the summary for this
part is that we are
having a model consolidation.
We can now do the high-level
reasoning and low-level control
in one model.
And the low-level
control part is
what excites me,
because it's so far
away from the traditional
language model domain.
It's so different.
And it shows signs of life
that we can trickle down
a lot more than we used
to think is possible.
And we can scale the pretraining
of visual language models,
as well as scaling
robotics data.
And we observe more
and more positive
transfer-- model benefiting
from diverse joint training
across internet-scale
language, vision,
and vision-language domains.
So I noticed that we are
close to running out of time.
So I will just very quickly go
through the second part, which
I think is also interesting.
It's to find new interfaces
of language models.
But I would only talk
at a very high level.
So language models,
as we can see,
can directly output
action tokens
if we found an action
representation.
So we can treat an action as yet
another language to the language
model.
So a language model
can do translation.
So it should be able to
generate action as well.
But that requires fine tuning.
Can we do it
without fine tuning,
or can we generate
more expressive actions
that is beyond the
scope of fine tuning?
So that is about finding
the right interface.
So previously, we have
already established
that language model doesn't
have an action interface.
If it has an action interface,
it's not as effective.
So what is the best
interface between language
and a lot of actions?
I would argue the best interface
between a language model
and a lot of actions
is reward functions.
And reward functions
is universal.
It has been used in
reinforcement learning.
And it's also a
reparameterization of actions.
What is action?
Let me-- let's see if I
want to pick up this bottle.
And I can say, what is a skill?
A skill is a mapping between
my observation and my action.
So the mapping between
my observation and action
can be seen as a skill.
But a skill can have an
alternative definition,
which is a set of constraints
and a set of objectives.
So picking up the bottle means
the bottle is in my right hand,
and the bottle is off
a supporting surface.
That means picking up.
And how do I pick it up
doesn't really matter.
That's a more-- to its broader
sense, the definition of skills
is more transferable
between different skills.
And the constraints
and objectives
can be represented as rewards.
So we can ask the language
model to generate these reward
functions.
And then there is an optimizer.
It could be reinforced
learning, or it
could be model
predictive control that
optimizes for those rewards,
and then run it on the robot.
So what is in the
reward translator?
Let's open a box.
So the reward
translator, basically,
is a two-stage process.
It's using the same
language model,
and it is using two
different prompts.
So the motion description
basically describes the motion.
So just now we found that
the language model can output
a description of how a
robot dog should stand up,
but it's not able
to achieve that.
But the motion description
is still sensible.
It still makes sense.
It gives you the right thing.
So we're just like, generate
this motion description,
and then we have a reward
translator, a reward coder that
translates this
motion description
into a piece of code that is
representing reward functions.
And these reward functions
cannot be directly executed
on the robot.
But it can go through
an optimization process
to learn how to achieve
those reward functions.
So we're using reward as the
interface between language model
and a low-level controller.
And for the
low-level controller,
we're using MuJoCo MPC, which
is a model predictive control
algorithm.
It's basically a
black box controller.
It samples a lot of
trajectories and finds
one that optimizes your reward.
And we tested it on a robot dog,
a quadruped robot, essentially,
and a dexterous manipulator.
So the dexterous manipulator
has an arm of six
or seven degrees of
freedom and a hand.
It's impossible to
control it because it
has so many degrees of freedom.
So it's highly challenging.
So just to showcase
some of the examples,
I omitted the motion
description part.
I only output the
reward code part.
So it seems that
the language model
is able to generate
the right reward
functions to make
the robot stand up
on two back feet like a human.
And now we are a little
bit more ambitious.
We know it can stand up.
Can we make the
robot do a moonwalk
while standing up like this?
So a moonwalk is
from Michael Jackson,
and it's very challenging.
How do we make the
robot to do it?
So it generates the
motion description
and generates the reward code.
But the motion is
not so correct-- not
exactly what we want.
The nice thing about
using a language model
and using the reward function
is that you can coach the robot.
You can go back and
explain what went wrong,
and ask the language
model to fix it.
So now we can actually say--
you're being very patient.
You say, moonwalk
means a robot should
walk backwards
while the feet swing
as if they are moving forward.
Such a great explanation.
Kudos to my colleague.
And correct your
answer, and also
make it work at the speed
of 0.5 meters per second.
And after you-- like
being very patient
and give it the
right instruction,
it's able to modify the
reward-- the motion descriptor
and also generate the right set
of rewards to make this happen.
And now you can teach
a robot to do moonwalk,
just by using the
language as an interface.
And one day we'll be able to do
this on the real robot as well.
Yes.
So the previous session, he
showed how the [INAUDIBLE]
big numbers, and you're
constraining them
to [? just ?] big numbers.
Here, how do you prevent it from
just hallucinating [INAUDIBLE]??
Right.
So that's a great question.
In this work, we are
not preventing it,
hallucination-- to
do hallucination
in a programmatic way.
We have a set of system
prompts or a set of rules
that is explaining the API.
After all, the
reward functions need
to be able to be compiled by
the optimizer, and then after--
so we do need to
have some check.
What's more, if it
doesn't compile,
we can just give the error
message to the language model.
It doesn't have to propagate
all the way to the motion
descriptor.
It can stay at the reward coder.
If there are errors,
please fix it.
So after that, it should
be able to fix it.
We can also chain
multiple tasks together.
Using this framework, we
can say, open the drawer.
Take the apple.
Put it into the drawer.
And close the door.
And it will be able to do that.
So we tried that.
Just using reward coder
is not good enough.
It's rather our two-stage prompt
is really, really helpful.
I think that's another
inspiration for other fields,
like when your domain is too
different from language domain,
maybe it would be good to find
an intermediate representation
and ask the language
model to explain
in that intermediate
representation
before it directly goes to a
more obscure representation.
And finally, we want to
transfer this to the real world.
But there is a challenge.
In simulation, it might
generate actions that
are too dexterous, like this.
This thing is not possible
to do in the real world.
So we add a few more regularizer
terms to stabilize the motion.
And we also run some state
estimation on the real robot
so that they understand
where is the cubes.
And then we can, in the
simulation, grab the motion,
and then achieve it
in the real world.
So here are some of the
execution in the real world.
So you can say, pick
up the Rubik's cube,
and it will generate
the motion to pick up
the Rubik's cube and the apple.
This is quite
different from RT-2.
The motions are quite smooth.
It's quite fast.
It's much faster than 3 hertz.
So here it can do 10
hertz, or even 30 hertz.
So it's comparable
with human speed.
All right, so that's
language to reward.
There's one last
thing that I want
to talk about in terms of
finding a new interface.
So a lot of time we have been
thinking about language model
as a semantic engine,
a semantic machine.
It understands semantics.
So, for example, you say the
student takes out the book.
You will say book.
A language model is able to
reason about such a sequence.
But if you do
low-level patterns,
like, if you just give
it obscure numbers,
what can you do?
It's actually a
low-level interface,
and we can open up the
low-level interface
to other language models and
ask it to do robotics tasks.
So in this paper, "Large
Language Models as General
Pattern Machines," we explore
using the low-level interface
of a large language model,
essentially asking it to reason
about different sequences.
And it's surprisingly
quite effective.
And it can solve tasks like
the ARC challenge and the PCFG.
And it can even do
sequence improvement.
So I will dig a little bit
into sequence improvement,
because that's quite
relevant to robotics.
So sequence improvement is that
you prompt the language model
with state, action,
and reward tuples.
And you just prompt
it with higher reward
and see if it can
generate actions
that achieve the higher reward.
So it's doing
reinforced learning,
or a reinforce learning
like thing, but in context.
So this is quite amazing.
So previously, you would need a
dedicated algorithm collecting
data, replay buffer to do
this reinforcement learning.
But now you can just build
everything in the language model
context by leveraging
the low-level interface
of a language model.
And with that, we can
actually do something
like clicker training.
So if we are not very familiar
with clicker training,
this is how you can do that.
You can have a
dog, and you can--
when it does the right
thing, you give it a reward
by clicking.
The other hand.
So you can-- so the
clicker training
is giving the agent a reward.
And we can now use
clicker training
to train robots as well.
So here the robot is exploring.
But I would give a click
when it does the right thing
or towards the right direction.
And over time, it
will be able to push
the bag of chips, which is the
objective of this training.
So you can do this entire
decision transformer-like
operation, but
purely in context,
by just giving a language
model a bunch of patterns
and ask it to figure out what is
the regularity of this sequence.
And this way, it can
generate new actions
to improve a previous sequence.
So for the language
model, we can
find new interfaces that are
more suitable for teaching
it low-level skills.
Reward is a bridge
of the language model
and the low-level control.
And we can fully leverage
it as a universal interface.
And we can optimize
in real time.
Sometimes it outperforms,
generating action directly.
So it really motivates to
use the reward functions
as an interface.
And in the language model
as general pattern machines,
we can use language model
beyond the semantic tasks.
We can ask it to reason
low level things.
And also, robotics as a domain
rich of sequence transformation,
and sequence completion, and
sequence improvement tasks.
So we can really
study the lower level
mechanisms of language models.
And the key takeaway is that--
for this talk is that we
are seeing more and more use
of foundation models, not
only on the semantic reasoning
side of robotics, but more on
the dexterous, on the generating
actions, on the
lower level embodied
intelligence side of robotics.
And we need to rethink
the scaling law
of robotics and transformer.
How do we scale it with
limited amount of data?
We have a new recipe for
scaling robot model and data
in RT-2, which shows that you
can do more with the same data.
With essentially RT-1
data plus internet data,
you can generalize
to a lot more things.
And RT-X shows that you can
do a lot more with more data.
There is also benefits to
collecting more robotics data.
And there is positive
transfers everywhere.
And part two, in terms of new
interfaces for language models,
I think it's worth
for the robotics field
to think about developing
new and lower level
interface to language
models, which facilitate
learning low level skills.
With that, I would like
to conclude my talk.
And if you find it
interesting, there
are a lot of references
for you to look into.
And special thanks to my team,
Google DeepMind Robotics Team.
So we are at the forefront
of developing foundation
models for robotics.
And stay tuned for
more in the future.
Thank you.
Yes.
You mentioned that
[INAUDIBLE] numbers
are difficult for
large language models.
But if you're just generating
the action tokens themselves,
like no [INAUDIBLE],,
or whatever you had,
an example, why don't you
just have a linear layer
appended to the transformer
that would just generate numbers
from 0 to 25 or whatever it is?
Yeah.
The question is that if we are--
the large language models
have difficulty understanding
numbers, why don't
we use a linear layer
to output the action directly?
I think-- so language models are
difficult to understand numbers,
but sometimes we still want
it to bring in knowledge
from the pretraining mixture.
If I want-- if I have a new
layer, like the new layer is not
present in the pretraining, so
how do I expect it to transfer?
I think that's an
interesting question.
But at the same time,
I don't necessarily
think using the raw numbers
is the right interface.
We probably could do some
action representation learning
to learn our representation.
And the language model can
output that representation.
So we're still trying
to figure out what
is the right representation.
So among the
representations that we
have tried before,
like decimal numbers,
float the numbers,
extra tokens, we
find that just using
numbers or actual tokens
would be good enough.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] three different
[INAUDIBLE] more promising.
Yeah, I think both directions
are worth exploring.
There are different
advantages of generating--
generating action
directly, I think
it borrows the autoregressive
nature of language modeling.
And it aligns with a
lot of other tasks,
like visual question
answering really well.
The limitation is that then
when you're generating actions,
it's heavily regularized.
Can you generate
dexterous actions
that is so out-of-distribution?
That is kind of difficult. The
language to reward actually
brings a page of the book
of traditional robotics,
this optimization based or
model predictor control.
And you can also take into,
let's say, safety constraints
more easily.
It can generate more
diverse actions.
Maybe one recipe is to
generate a lot of data
with the language to reward
system and distill them
into a transformer,
because then you
are imbuing your
large language model
with all this other desirable--
the language to reward itself,
I don't know how scalable it is.
We're not fine tuning
the language model,
so maybe you are
limited to what--
you are at the mercy of the
training data of the language
model.
The language model
can do more work,
because it knows
what moonwalk is.
It roughly knows how to do that.
But if you want to scale
to completely new things,
maybe you can use the
language to reward
to bootstrap your
data generation,
and then put it into
the other policy.
What's the next direction
Google is pursuing?
So it's like, is the language
as rewards the right direction
or is it more like scaling
out into [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah, I think that's
a good question.
So the scaling being the end of
the lecture, that has a joke.
But I'm being quite serious.
It's actually a
promising recipe.
So we have been--
everybody is believing in the
power of the scaling rule.
So just by giving it more
data, giving it more compute,
you will see interesting kind
of capabilities coming out.
[INAUDIBLE] GPT2 to
GPT was a big jump.
So do you think we are
ready for robotics to have
that jump, where we can--
where do you see
the gaps currently?
I still think we are not quite--
we don't quite have enough data.
I think that's still probably
the biggest bottleneck.
So we are trying to find ways
to do more with limited data.
And we are trying to
collect more data.
And I think it needs
some time for us
to accumulate enough data.
And currently, I
say we have signs
of life for positive transfer.
But in language
models, people don't
talk about positive
transfers anymore,
because it's so commonplace.
You see it everywhere.
And robotics is not
at that stage yet.
How much is your team thinking
about safety and alignment?
Are you just, right now, relying
on the ethics that emerge
from the large language models?
It won't tell you to kill
somebody to achieve an effect.
Yeah, that's a
very good question.
Actually, we take safety
very, very seriously,
because all of the other domains
of developing language models,
it doesn't have direct
impact on the physical world.
But here, it could have
potential harm to humans
and to the environment.
And Gary Marcus actually gave a
comment previously to our work.
What if you say, bring
out a bowl, feed the cat,
and put it in the dishwasher.
Would it put the cat
in the dishwasher?
If it misunderstands,
actually, it
will have a catastrophic
failure case.
We take safety carefully by
designing hardware and software
safety layers.
And there are also some
constitutional safety thing that
is coming out sometime soon.
I cannot tell much
details right now,
but sometime soon we'll
release some work.
Is it something like,
"If there's a human,
just don't interact"?
Well, no, no, no, I think it's a
little bit more nuanced and more
detailed than that.
But we do take safety
quite seriously.
And in some of our
experiments, actually,
the robot finger
would break off,
because it cannot apply enough
force to an environment.
So this is yet another
way of ensuring safety.
Can we have some
visual language model
as a supervisor or
something to [INAUDIBLE]??
And maybe this is kind
of like [INAUDIBLE],,
but both in some [INAUDIBLE].
Right, right.
Yeah, I think it
would be possible.
[INAUDIBLE] larger experience,
depending on [INAUDIBLE]..
Thank you for the great talk.
Cool, cool.